Finding Aid for Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, Lansing area chapter records 1972-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Parents,Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, Lansing area chapter records 1972-1999, 1981-1999
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays (Lansing Area)
0.75 linear feet
Lansing area chapter of national non-profit organization established to promote health and well-being of gays, lesbians, and bisexuals and their families and friends. Records include background information; administrative files; topical files detailing activities of the chapter; scanned photographic images; and a videocassette.
00140 Bw 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were accessioned from the Lansing area chapter in July of 2000. Donor no. 8993.
The record group is open for research.
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, or PFLAG, was established in 1981 as a national non-profit organization, to promote the health and well-being of gays, lesbians, and bisexuals and their families and friends through support services, education, and civil rights advocacy on the national and local level. Currently PFLAG has a membership of over 80,000 households and more than 425 affiliates worldwide, a network which is developed, resourced and serviced by the PFLAG national office in Washington D.C., a national Board of Directors, and a Regional Directors' Council.
The idea for PFLAG was conceived by Jeanne Manford, a fourth-grade teacher in New York City, who in 1972 marched with her gay son in the New York City gay pride parade bearing the sign, "Parents of Gays: Unite in Support of Our Children." Manford was inundated with requests from lesbians, gays, and parents to speak with other parents and to participate in panel discussions and interviews throughout the country. In 1973 she formed a small New York City support group called Parents of Gays. In 1974, Manford helping Adela and Larry Starr to form a group in Los Angeles in 1974. Similar support groups began forming across the country, and in 1979 they met in Washington, DC at the first National March for Gay and Lesbian Rights. In 1981 the twenty groups that had been created met in the Starr's home in Los Angeles and formed the Federation of Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, or Parents FLAG. A five-member Board of Directors was created, and Adele Starr became the organization's first president. The organization relocated its headquarters to Denver in 1987, and to a permanent national office in Washington, D.C. in 1988. To accommodate local chapters, as well as a growing national profile, the organization restructured in 1993, establishing an affiliation process for chapters, making board seats an elected position, and changing its name to Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays.
The Lansing Area Chapter of PFLAG began in Okemos, Michigan in 1981, as a member group of the Federation of Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays. The group held its first official Board/Action Committee meeting as Parents FLAG/ Lansing Area in 1988, led by president Jean Ross. In 1996, under then and current president Carolyn Chial-Telder, the group completed its application for Chartered Chapter status under the reorganized national PFLAG organization.
For more information on the history and current activities of PFLAG, see the National PFLAG website at: http://www.pflag.org and the Lansing Area Chapter website at: http://members.aol.com/pflaglans/pflaglans.html.
The records of the Lansing Area Chapter of PFLAG, 1972-1995 (.75 linear ft.) document the founding, administration and programs of the Lansing chapter of a national organization that provides service and support to gays, lesbians, and bisexuals and their families and friends. The records have been organized into four series: Background and History, 1972-1995, Administrative, 1982-1999, Topical Files, 1988-1999, and Audio Visual, 1980s-1996.
Subjects:
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays. Lansing Area chapter.; Gays--Michigan--Lansing.; Parents of gays--Michigan--Lansing.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays. Lansing Area chapter.; Parents of gays--Michigan--Lansing.
Genre/Form:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Background and History 1972-1995
  Background and History, 1972-1995 contains materials documenting the group's foundation and early years. Included are clippings of early press announcements and news articles, correspondence relating to early outreach activities, as well as the first year of Board/Action Committee minutes. Of note within the folder "Brochures, Clippings, and Outreach, 1981-1986" is a memo put out by the Federation of Parents & Friends of Lesbians and Gays regarding its objectives and rules for membership application. Also included are Lansing Area Chapter bylaws and a packet of informational material on the history, mission, and policy stands of the national organization.
  - Board/Action Committee Minutes 1988 (Box 1)
  - Brochures, Clippings, and Outreach 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1995 (Box 1)
  - "Informational Material" (Box 1)
    History, Mission, Policy Statements, Etc.
- Administrative 1982-1999
  Administrative, 1982-1999 is the largest series and consists of materials produced by the Lansing Area Chapter in the course of its activities. Of note are Meeting Notes from 1995-1999 and a substantial run of the Lansing Area Chapter Newsletter,1988-1999. Also of particular interest are correspondence files which document the types of activities and issues dealt with by the president and board.
  - Book, Pamphlet, Tape, and Video lists 1982-1986 (Box 1)
  - Brochures and Fliers 1984-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights Ordinance 1996 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Carolyn Chial-Telder 1995-1998 (Box 1)
    - General 1994-1999 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Notes 1995-1999 (Box 1)
  - Membership/Phone lists 1988-1995 (Box 1)
  - Member Obituaries 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - National Convention Program October 20-23, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Newsletter 1988-1999 (Box 1)
  - Program Ideas/Newsletter Filler (Box 1)
  - Project 10 Background Material (Box 1)
  - Publicity Mailings 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - State Meeting, Central Michigan University 1996 (Box 1)
  - Transsexuality, Correspondence and Information 1987-1991 (Box 1)
- Topical Files 1988-1999
  Topical Files, 1988-1999 contains materials collected by the Chapter on issues relating to the Lansing area Gay and Lesbian community. Included are materials regarding other area organizations, such as PRISM, a support group for Lesbian and Gay youth, as well as clippings from area newspapers and two "Year in Review" collections of news articles from Michigan State University's State News regarding campus Gay and Lesbian activities and issues.
  - Buttons, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - "John Allen's Journal," June-October 1996 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Gay/Lesbian Community Activities, Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - News Articles
    - Miscellaneous 1988-1999 (Box 1)
    - State News (Michigan State University), 1997-1998, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - PRISM 1993-1999 (Box 1)
  - "Tri-county HIV Resource Guide" (Box 1)
- Audio Visual 1980s-1996
  Audio Visual, 1980s-1996 consists of one folder of eleven scanned photographs (all labelled) of annual picnics, marches, and other events, as well as one VHS videocassette.
  - Photographs (scanned), 1980s-1993 (Box 1)
  - Videocassette, "Love is All it Takes to Make a Family," 1996, running time, 29:41 (Box 1)